Tatry IT
Good evening.
Welcome to another Tatry IT meetup.
Tatry IT
I always say that it is a name that is not entirely correct,
because as you can see today,
we are not only talking about IT topics,
but also about topics that are not entirely IT,
that are around IT.
It is more of a technical, scientific,
we can call it lifestyle,
self-realization, productivity.
So everything that is related to the fact
that a person can somehow move,
educate and so on.
I am saying this because I see people here
whom I have not yet seen so far.
So I am glad that anyone who is new here
has come between us.
We met in such a standard number.
Of those 10 to 15 people,
it is usually such a perfect number
for the city of Poprad,
since this region is neither big
nor the city is big.
And if you think that there are few of us,
you don't have to worry at all,
because even in other larger cities
there is a standard number of 10, 15.
If someone is interested,
there can be 25 people or even 50.
But today we already have the 35th meetup.
I will give this slide now
so that I can remember it.
So we have already met 35 times
here in Coworking Poprad.
We have not been anywhere else so far.
Thank you, Tomáš, that we can be here.
Tomáš is in the back and he is directing it here.
Today's topic, as I mentioned,
will not be direct or purely technical.
IT will be more about productivity,
about self-development.
I am very happy about the opportunity
because despite the fact that
I have been trying to be
either productive
or not dependent on technology,
but rather have technology
as my tool,
a tool to serve me,
it is difficult.
So I am curious what I will learn today.
I will not introduce myself
because I will introduce myself in a moment.
So this is our presenter.
And if you have any questions,
I assume you can ask them directly
or you can leave them for later.
Or you can use Slido
with the hashtag TatriIT.
So if you know how to use Slido
and you do not want to interrupt
and you want to ask a question
and you want to ask at the end,
feel free to use Slido.
We will take a look at it.
Those of you who are not in our newsletter,
I will repeat it,
you can sign up for the newsletter.
Just go to www.tatriit.sk
and if you wait a moment,
maybe 5 seconds,
a pop-up will pop up
and you can write your name and email.
And you will be notified
when there will be a new meetup.
And in connection with that,
we have three more terms for the next meetup
until June.
That means that we will meet
the closest after this meetup in April.
Then we will meet in May
and even in June.
That term is not yet completely clear.
But we can tell you
that there will be one non-technical theme,
one very practical technical theme
and then the last one will be very technical.
So that's okay,
we will meet on the 24th.
On the 24th,
Miki Plichta R
will talk to us
about LinkedIn.
How to prepare your LinkedIn account.
It is not enough
to write a CV,
you have to present yourself
on social networks.
So Miki Plichta will come to us
and talk about LinkedIn profiles
for technical people
or for scientists.
Let me know.
Everyone needs this kind of information.
Let's get to our topic today.
Samo, welcome to us
for the second time.
It's good to see you there.
So you are not a newbie,
but you are here
all the time.
So come on
and tell us
what will be your topic
and your stage.
Thank you.
Let's start this presentation.
It was supposed to be a video,
but you don't notice it.
There should be more of them,
but let's go.
You are a digital child.
This is something
I had to admit
roughly two years ago,
more than two years ago.
It was the reality
with which I met
on my journey of life.
And it looked
like this.
Imagine that the camera
is moving now on this video
and shows you the whole room,
the computer,
the screen.
And this is what it looks like
when you are a digital child.
You simply don't see the border
between the digital world
and the real world.
Everything is merged into one.
You are a digital child
when technology is in your way
to movement.
You spend an enormous amount
of online content consumption.
It can be on any social network.
It can be a TV series.
You work remotely
and go straight for the screen
from the bed.
You are a digital child
when technologies
do not help you
to be fully concentrated in your work.
You are interrupted by irrelevant notifications
at any time during your work.
You don't have enough concentration
and every moment you need
a dopamine shot
to find something more interesting
than your work.
I don't know.
You are a digital child
when technologies have a negative impact
on your relationship development.
Instead of meeting people
in person,
you prefer to live
in your bubble behind a screen
and simply don't want
to confront yourself
through the people you meet.
Feel free to post
as you see fit.
Simply, technology
prevents you from living
fully in your present moment.
This is something I grew up with
in my life.
I needed to make a change.
I needed to transform.
This is my way
to digital freedom.
Or how I got
technology under control in my life.
Imagine this.
It was supposed to be a video.
It is simply a man
who is connected to cables
that represent
various applications we use.
To go through
transformation,
the technologies
start to serve the man
and not the man
who serves the technology
as it is sometimes in our lives.
In my case, it was certainly so.
Before I start
with my story,
I will talk about myself.
I am a web programmer
and I make projects
that reflect my values.
This is my way to digital freedom
or digital freedom
if we translate it from English.
Free with tech.
Let's get started.
Get ready
because this will be a tough ride.
Digital native.
What is this term?
I am a man who grew up
with a phone in his hand.
At that time, various communication tools
such as Pockets,
Facebook,
I installed it on my phone.
I was among the first
million users.
I had my first phone in my hands
in the third year of primary school.
This is a bit of a misunderstanding
of my context.
I continue my education.
I thank my parents
that they really led me to active movement.
And until today it happened to me
as you can see in these photos
with my friends in the mountains
and on various bicycle routes.
However, the reality was such
that technologies in my life
took the first place
after some time.
Simply yes.
I went to trainings,
I did sports,
I tried to listen to my parents.
Let's say it was like that at the time.
Because they advised me
not to sit so long
behind the computer.
Of course, we didn't know
what was connected to it.
Because it was a new world
of games.
Imagine the picture
where there is a computer game
on the screen
and some kind of digital tool
where I create graphics
and code, programs.
Just like this
my journey started.
First it was a lot of games
then it was the end of primary school
graphic design and what not.
But they were not the same
in the world.
But the boundaries
Simply, the digital space was gaining me more and more, that was the reality.
Here you can imagine, the boy has the digital glasses on him and the real world is fighting with the digital world.
The switching of these two worlds there is simple.
And the digital one was gradually winning in my life.
Try to guess, maybe, what color represents, when it comes to time allocation, in a specific day,
maybe in my age, when I was in high school, what color represents the time behind the screen, in your opinion?
Any other tips?
All of them? That would be a good extreme, then.
I was the only one who got to that point, even though I was programming 24 hours a day.
Thank you for the tips.
You were very close.
And you were right. Red color, almost 10 hours a day, even 10 hours a day.
It was games, it was a combination of games and the creation of something digital.
The computer created a very significant amount of that time in my life.
So, the tax was clear.
In the 20s, I counted it, I spent one year just playing games.
Just playing games, there was no time for mobile phones and so on.
It's more than 8,000 hours, right?
Imagine you're sitting at the computer.
Imagine, there's a tax there.
And it's actually that I'm organized in that digital space, but I really can't go in the direction I need or want.
I'm connected on social networks with various people, friends or not.
And the real connection, as if when I meet, it's not there at all.
I'm informed by various channels, but I can't focus at the moment on what I need.
And so I went from this world, primary, secondary school, I went to the world of high school.
And there, of course, it was very natural for me.
That yes, a programmer.
Great.
I can sit at the computer, it doesn't make me a problem in ten-hour shifts.
So I'm going to program tasks instead of playing games.
It was so natural.
That's how I decided.
And it was in the same way some kind of comfort zone for me all the time.
I was it myself, a computer, it was digital communication.
Maybe even an excessive amount of digital communication.
Non-stop internet connection.
The management of information in a digital space.
Really.
During high school, I thought so.
It was probably 10-15 notebooks that I wrote.
Most of the things were in a digital space, really.
More about that, that a person studies programming and mostly the right time on the computer.
So I decided to take a radical step in life.
Hey, I need to mention that I started working at a high level and I had a lot of flexibility at work.
It was great at work.
But a person simply has to grasp their life into their own hands.
And they have to set some limits.
That's how I realized it at that time, after high school.
And in fact, a radical step came when I started digital applications.
All the solutions that I have in my life, for example, evidence of some things I want to do.
Tudučka, notes, digital calendars.
Digital communication.
In short, everything was in that digital space.
A very important part of my life.
And I decided that this doesn't work this way.
Because there was the joint debt that I presented before.
And so I took a journal, a piece of paper, a notebook.
I migrated everything there.
All the information that was important to me.
Everything I need to do.
All my thoughts.
In short, digital stopped working for me.
That's how I gave up.
So, 100% of the attention was in my hands.
And someone would say that it's counterproductive.
Because we have all the digital tools here.
Why not use them?
But in this starting point, when a person finds himself,
that he is simply influenced by these technologies to such an extent
that they rather disrupt his life in these three main areas of life
than develop it in the positive direction.
So it was inevitable.
Really.
Take a pen and start writing.
It turned out that writing is good.
In fact, it will teach a person to think a little better.
And so on.
Maybe you all know it.
But really, when a person grows up with technologies
and maybe he is not used to writing at all,
it will work out.
That's how some kind of purposeful existence started in my life.
That's why I started writing.
When a person starts to realize things more,
I hope I've crossed the line.
But I don't think I have.
Okay.
We have a problem here.
It works for me.
That's fine.
It doesn't work at all.
Okay.
I'll try it.
It's lagging.
It doesn't work.
There's a high response, I guess.
This is the previous slide.
We have to go on now.
So what worked for me?
The first building pillar on the way to digital freedom,
as I mentioned.
It didn't work for me.
I left my phone without a critical application.
I really had an e-mail and a number.
For a certain period of time.
It really wasn't necessary for the digital space to be limited
and for me not to be so accessible.
I had to send a diary out of the digital space.
Because we can take an application to write a diary,
but I was set up in such a way
that I didn't see it as a solution.
So that's why I started writing.
And marking my habits on a daily basis.
And some reflection.
So it was definitely a very important point
on this journey of mine
to look at the past every day.
To reflect on the past.
And I just knew how to move on.
And it all worked out on paper.
It was the goal.
Can we go on?
So, technologies need to be used.
Why are they here?
Why would we work like this on paper?
Yes.
After a while, I got to the point
that I can make some things more effective,
but it was already a different starting point.
It was already a point that some things
weren't as effective.
And the first application,
which I learned,
was the digital calendar.
I was more productive thanks to it.
I didn't have to write it down on paper
what I should do when.
So there was a question
where to draw the line
between the real world
and the digital world.
That allowed me to take that step.
To write everything.
So that allowed me to draw the line.
Where do I put it?
Where is the writing poison?
How do I say it?
The digital calendar.
Then the social networks.
I also used them,
but after a while,
some of them maybe
bring motivation to the movement.
Why not bring them back
into your life?
Then the other networks
really didn't help me.
The energy there
wasn't good enough.
I don't need to know
what someone is doing.
I met someone ten years ago
and what he's doing in Malta.
And so on.
So I didn't need
some social networks.
And everyone answers this question
on their own.
And the simple goal for me is
to hold on to some
positive energy.
So,
my attention
was really a priority.
Number one.
And by bringing these digital tools
into my life,
I tried to keep it
so that it would be
like that forever.
Simply,
to know how to focus
on the present moment.
And those tools
shouldn't take
too much
attention.
If a digital tool
doesn't serve
in the development
of relationships,
movement
or
work,
if it's not
really a positive influence,
then I'll simply
say goodbye to it.
We can go on.
So, yes.
What works for me
when it comes to
digital minimalism?
Maybe another principle
on the way
to digital freedom.
Writing things
into a diary
is the first step.
But the diary
is not always with me.
I don't want
the paper
to get wet
in the rain.
So,
of course,
I start using applications.
This is where
the most important
point comes in.
What I still use
today,
I simply
write it
into the application
but then I rewrite it
because I simply
found out
that writing
is really important.
A person
will filter
a lot of things
he realizes.
So,
the diary
didn't go anywhere.
It really remained
a central system
for me.
That is to say,
the point came
and I said
that technology
is an expansion
and not
a basis
of my life.
And this is something
that one needs
to realize
when he grew up
with technologies.
Simply,
the digital world
can come
as close
and as deeply
under the skin
as it is.
Simply,
this border
is invisible.
As I said.
Likewise,
the strategies
of Zero Inbox
you may know,
zero storage, or it's just that
as soon as I receive an email,
I need to either archive it, delete it,
or put it away. The goal is
to keep the inbox empty, so it helps
with concentration and so that we don't waste too much time
in applications. I started asking myself
sometimes, when we write on paper,
where would our computing power go? Maybe
when visualizing data, when we want to see some historical data, maybe how my
habits develop in time, maybe I want to communicate
online. These questions,
where does computing power go,
helped me to
bring these digital tools into my life, but
in a more conscious way. And I knew why I had them.
The HESEL report is also a very good
strategy to reflect on our digital
stop, and that is where the information about us is located.
I have a list of all the services I use online, and it's
a central place where I can see
what I need and what I don't need. These are some
digital dependencies that we can influence and reflect on.
Can we go on?
So, I live with a goal, I am focused,
and what else could there be as a third pillar
on the way to digital freedom? I discovered that
it is greater control and privacy.
When, how, what to do online.
To perceive the internet as a public space, despite the fact that
it is secure, of course, our communication cannot read it,
but as a human being, there is a border between paper
and technology, so it is more sensitive to its privacy,
and in fact, it evaluates whether the information can be
on the internet, whether I am comfortable to leave the information on the internet.
Let's imagine control as
some piece of paper where emails are printed,
maybe some of you do it, and you want to be sure
that you have the email, you have it, it simply does not disappear anywhere in the matrix.
We can imagine privacy as
some envelope that comes in mail to me and was not broken,
simply no one read it. These questions are in the digital space,
they are here and they need to be asked. Who has my information, who has access to it?
Are my information a product?
Because the service is free. How can the service work when it is free
and I use it? That is the question. And I want these
my data to be used, let's say, for advertising purposes
or something.
Data transfer. If I create
some file in the Apple ecosystem, I can look at this file
on Windows. I can export data
from the system to which I decided to use it.
I can transfer my data from one service to another. What are the dependencies there?
Does the service allow me to erase my data?
All these questions are related to our digital step
and they started to show up in my life. Where do I want
my information to be stored? Of course, if I want
complete control,
I can run a cloud server at home and have 100% control,
but there is already some responsibility for the safety of these data.
We no longer outsource it to any company to take care of it. But we have
the control and there is the possibility.
These are some things that I am discovering now. This is the third point on my path.
The third is the last. That is,
the current situation is such that people probably install applications
and do not think about where the information is, who has access to them.
When a person gradually goes through
the awareness of digital minimalism, he starts to solve these questions.
At least that's how it was on my path. And it still is. The path continues.
This is not the final state. What worked for me
regarding technological independence?
This slide is a bit strange, sorry.
There is a link digitalsloboda.sk, so please,
if you want, you can come there later, there is also a quiz
I will get to later, but these slides with my recommendations
or what works for me are available on this web.
I will just mention a few types.
Diversification of online services providers.
It is nice to be Apple, Google, Microsoft,
but it is really easy to work together,
only that this is what we let ourselves be drawn into.
The more we use from one provider, the easier it is for him
to get even more of our information.
Diversification of providers, the use of various services,
notes, calendar, SEO manager, various providers.
It is nice to see the boundaries.
What does a provider allow us to do?
What not?
I can also evaluate whether our digital platform
has something to do with that provider.
The use of email alias.
An email contains our name and address.
We can reveal our identity to it.
That is why, for example,
the magic journal 1234
alias.sk,
sends messages to samuel-gmail.sk.
Maybe a bit of a controversial opinion
regarding online communication,
for example, direct communication
via Whatsapp, Facebook,
or whatever you use,
to perceive it as a meeting on the street.
I see my friends,
we talk,
we say goodbye at the end,
but this is the end.
I simply do not use the application
for communication,
in order to store my whole history
with this person.
As soon as there is some useful information
for my future,
I extract it to some external system,
for example, to my diary.
In this case, I eliminate the need
to go to the application
if I want to read something.
Simply, everything important
is independent of the provider and service provider.
Also,
the application is divided
into several levels.
We have some critical warnings,
we want them to keep coming,
we have some normal warnings,
there may be some number
on the application icon
in the phone,
and then I open it
when I need it,
when I have time for it,
when I have some free time.
And then there are some unwanted warnings,
so go through the settings
of the application.
So, maybe one more tip,
there are more of them,
but change the endless
content records to the final ones.
So, really,
in such two phases,
go through the social network
in the first one,
maybe in five minutes,
the endless record,
choose something interesting from it,
store it in the record
that is final, which I control,
empty it,
and when I empty the record
that I have filled,
it is the final point
when I finish
and look at the endless records
in the social networks.
So,
before this transformation,
really glued to the screen,
I lost,
I would say,
some minimal ability
to focus on the longer term
and the use of pre-selected applications
and settings,
I didn't think about
any digital step at all.
And then,
after the transformation,
I don't know what is doomscrolling,
simply, yes, I am here and now,
I work with people around me,
and of course,
those influences are there all the time,
I grew up with technologies
and it influenced me,
but it can be handled,
gradually it works.
In my reality,
it is not some basis,
there is a clear border,
I have gradually realized it.
Really,
timeliness in privacy
is another aspect
that has developed in me,
so really,
to realize what I publicize,
the Internet is a public space
where we are not 100% sure
that our information
was not accessed by someone who did not have it,
and easy migration,
I am not dependent
simply
on one giga provider,
I have services
divided
among various.
Was it worth it?
I counted it like that,
20 minutes a day,
in the last two years
I have been running a diary,
and I take it as a great success,
at least from my point of view,
it was very beneficial,
because I really said
yes to myself,
self-awareness,
then
I found out that apps
are an extension of life
and not some basis,
and technological independence
is some kind of control
over your digital status,
so I realize
what the providers and services
have about me,
I never realize everything,
but yes,
I take the Internet
as a public space
and I am sensitive
to my privacy
and to data.
Here is another video
for the end,
the transformation
of a man who is
entangled by threats
and the digital space
devours him,
until he goes
to the right place,
but I need him
to the right limits,
and if we don't see them,
the realities seem to dominate
even the digital reality,
and I just don't see
the waste bin
that is full in the kitchen
and I need to take it away.
I decided to share
this story publicly,
so I write blogs on Substack,
I also create YouTube videos
and I want to communicate
to the world
that there are people
like me here
and I would be glad
if only one person
is inspired,
it will mean a lot to me
because I have gone
through the whole transformation
and it really causes
a great damage
in a person's life
when he spends so much
on the computer,
a great concentration
in work,
and this was my story
and this is how I grew up
in the digital freedom
and here are some links
at the end.
Thank you for your attention
and I will be glad
to talk about this topic.
Is the microphone working?
Yes, good.
Thank you very much
for such an honest
introduction to your way.
We will ask questions
in the classroom,
so I will give you the microphone
to be recorded,
because the questions
that are in the audience
are not heard on the video recording.
Who wants to start?
Because I have a lot of questions
and we also have questions
on the slide.
So, what do you want to start with?
The application,
but we need it here
because this is a tool.
Let's start from the beginning.
Have you ever tried going out
without a phone
or having a phone
that can only call
via SOS?
I think from the point of view
of concentration
on the real world.
Ondrej signed.
Without a phone,
I have a phone,
but I have it so limited
that I am there at that moment.
I am where I am
and when I need it,
I pull it out of the pocket,
but it is minimal.
I think about whether there are such moments.
Maybe you can also tell the audience
if you go somewhere like this.
But I even have hours
and those hours do not have a SIM card,
so I can really disconnect
and I can record things
even if I don't have a phone with me.
But you can imagine it, right?
I know, I know.
You got nervous.
I can imagine it, of course.
I am glad
when I have such a detox
from time to time.
What does a phone look like to me?
But we live in a digital age,
there are a lot of things on the Internet
and there are very few
moments like that, really.
I have to admit that
the phone is very often.
OK, I have a phone with me
and I have to ask you
a related question.
When you disconnected completely,
when you turned off everything,
what signs did you feel?
I mean, when a person
is abstinent,
exactly like that.
Have any experts talked about it?
Well,
there was a lot of writing
at that time.
The time was really big
and all the attention was mine
and no one stole it from me,
no digital device.
And hey,
that was probably the sign of abstinence.
I just needed to filter it
on the paper
and really reflect on the situation in life.
The habit of reflecting
allowed me
to realize how much
technology has affected my life
and to improve it.
So I understand it that
your counter-step
was to compensate it with writing.
Yes.
When you wanted to use your phone,
you used your diary
and wrote something.
We are all here
in the technological world.
Sometimes I go out
without a phone,
but not far, like 2 km.
So that's why I use my phone
as a safety device.
I go running, cycling,
because I have it.
But I was still
2 km without a phone.
That's all I can say.
And that's why
I'm interested in
how you solved it,
because you can't get rid of it
every day,
like when there are other dependencies.
That's probably my answer.
That's my extreme decision.
I went through detox
and deactivated my social networks
and so on.
I tried these approaches
in my life.
But then it was such an extreme point
that I realized
that the digital space
doesn't work for me
and I needed to cut with it.
Maybe it's a bit
a unique case, I don't know.
So your motivation was much stronger
than the signs.
Yes.
Any other questions?
We can go to the next one.
The magician is asking about learning.
Hmm.
No, no,
only the magician is learning.
Anyone? I'm reading.
Aren't you starting to be paranoid?
You solve alias and personal data on the Internet.
How does it relate to dependence
on technologies and digital freedom?
Okay, good question.
Good question, very good.
Hey, that's...
Maybe I mentioned it wrong
on my way, I don't know.
I've given it a name so far,
technological independence.
It made sense to me,
because after the time
when I had technologies again
in my life,
I started to think
about my
digital feet
and simply about some control
of who has my data.
So...
It can sound like that, yes.
That I'm paranoid
and that I solve problems.
Really, when we publish something on the Internet,
it's really public.
And why would I ever solve some alias,
if I can really identify myself
with some other strategies
for fingerprinting.
But there are some regulations
that we know
as consumers,
as users,
and we know how to do it.
I think these are steps to privacy
and to something that people
really want to grow.
We are not really there,
companies collect various information about us
and we are mostly okay with it.
So these strategies like alias
and data logging
really help us to realize
what is the digital feet
and maybe make other decisions
than we would do under normal circumstances.
So it's just
a new stage of development
on my way
and that's how I identified it
and presented it.
So we can talk about it further.
I don't know if this is enough.
The one who asked
the question was
a very important question.
Let's put it simply.
What games did you like?
Don't you miss any?
What is your view
on social games and quizzes?
And so on.
Great question.
Social games,
yes, not so much.
What I really envy
people who
when they grew up
lived more socially
social games were
their games
and not computer games.
I had computer games
rather than social games
and it was signed to me.
Maybe you can see it
through these
now.
I played a lot of CS.
I grew up on Counter-Strike.
I had a dream to be a professional player.
We fought at home with my parents
why do I spend 10 hours a day
playing Counter-Strike and I went to tournaments in Slovakia.
That was my goal.
That is part of my journey.
That is why I am here today.
I grew up like this
and I had to face these problems
because
it was signed.
So,
it was a easier question.
I play Counter-Strike.
Do you still play it?
I want to, but
the limits are clear.
It is there 2 hours a month.
Okay.
Do you know the book
Digital Minimalism by Kala Newporta?
Have you read the book?
I know Kala Newporta very well
and I haven't read this book.
I have read Deep Work.
It was the first book
that I got from this author
and then it was Slow Productivity.
That was a very good topic
that he wrote.
But Digital Minimalism, no.
I haven't read any book
about this principle
in my presentation.
But maybe
there are some types
that I don't know.
So feel free to ask.
Are you going to read them?
It would be fine
if I mentioned it like this.
Digital Minimalism
is such an authority
in this sphere
and it would certainly not be a shame
to read it.
So you have more time
That's true.
Okay.
I want something easier again.
But these are easy questions.
How long have you been
on this path?
On this path?
As I mentioned at the beginning,
during the year 2022
I took the radical step
that I wrote.
I cut off digital tools
and went to paper.
So the third year.
And you decided
that first of all
you go to paper completely.
Fine. You needed a reset.
I understand.
Then you came to
where you could improve,
optimize and speed up.
You got where you are.
Are you in the goal?
I'm definitely not in the goal.
And that's what I like the most
about Digital Minimalism.
This story doesn't end.
This story continues.
There will always be
the same questions.
Where are my data?
Do I need this app?
What does this app do in my life?
Does it make my life easier?
Does it help me grow in a certain sphere?
Or not?
So it's a path
and that's how I present it.
Okay.
And what about you and Minimalism
outside of digital space?
Are you trying to minimize
anonymity?
Yes.
I have a very minimalistic
room equipment.
And that's probably
the only thing
where it shows up.
I like Scandinavian
equipment methods.
I imagined it a little differently.
Some famous CEOs
to reduce
the burden of decisions
only wear black t-shirts
or blue t-shirts.
Are you aiming there?
I'm aiming there.
I think so.
I see in the audience
that the decision-making force
is just falling down
when I have to fix the color of the t-shirt.
It's on the way, I think.
You think this will be the way.
But I agree.
I don't know.
Just ask your questions.
The one who asked the question
and is not satisfied with the answer,
just ask.
Okay?
If my friend had a smaller t-shirt,
I wouldn't have to
advise her and praise
what she wants to wear.
That would save me time.
She's not here at all.
So it's okay.
But you can hear it.
You know we're recording.
Okay.
So you're trying to
minimize the decision-making.
Regarding the burden of decision-making
or the demands of decision-making,
Getting Things Done.
Yes, definitely.
It's closely related to that.
Have you tried it?
Do you plan it?
Don't you want it?
Is it complicated?
I have a personal hybrid approach to it.
I have Bullet Journal Method
and GTD.
Rather,
the phase when I get information,
Capture,
there is definitely
a realization of the importance
of the thing.
I use it often,
but not specifically.
I don't have it implemented specifically
in my life,
but I see the value
and I want to reveal it in the future.
Okay.
The concepts are often similar.
For those who don't know what GTD is,
Getting Things Done,
it's all done in Czech and Slovak.
I don't know what the translation is.
From my point of view,
it's an unfortunate name,
but that's just my opinion.
Who would like to learn more?
We have two meet-ups on this topic
in the archive on YouTube.
Getting Things Done.
You can watch it too.
Thank you.
How do you work on creating
the right habits
and how do you distinguish
good and bad habits?
I'll put it this way.
I have a very simple approach
to habits at the moment.
That's the minimalistic approach
in my life too.
I measure only six things
every day.
I don't know if I should present it like this.
I'm thinking if it's useful for you.
Of course.
Because we want to know
how you decide.
It doesn't have to mean
that I'm going to have the same process,
but maybe I don't have any.
As I mentioned,
my work is very flexible.
The most important thing for me
is to realize every day
what is needed,
what I need to focus on.
Because if there is unlimited flexibility,
that day probably won't turn out well
if I don't catch it.
My every day consists of
standing in the right time.
That's a great luxury
to be able to stand when I want.
But I want to achieve for myself
to stand in front of a certain time.
That's the first step in a given day.
Then I really want to do
the hardest task in a given day
that awaits me.
Here I need to define the day before.
So that's another habit.
Then I have to focus
on each of the important areas in life.
So work, relationships
and health.
Let's say running,
or going to the store,
or anything else related to movement.
I need to build personal relationships,
meeting with family, friends,
colleagues.
I also need to work on
projects I don't care about.
So I really
focused on
these five habits.
And the sixth is
preparing for the next day.
Of course, it's a day of reflection.
It's about realizing
what awaits me the next day
and what is the biggest,
the hardest task for the next day.
It's very simple.
I use this framework,
if I can call it that.
Maybe it will expand into the future.
But I think these are all
some good habits.
The magician is an action.
Is the answer enough?
Because I don't know how to react.
Yes?
Good.
I wanted to ask
an easy question.
How did you
make up for the time you spent
in the digital hell?
Are you learning something new?
Are you making wreaths?
At the moment,
as I mentioned,
you can see the link there,
I spend a lot of time on that.
I learn to make videos
and share my story.
It's a storytelling skill,
I would say.
And reading books
is definitely part of my life.
The latest autobiography
by Bill Gates,
Source Code,
I read it.
So books are definitely
a place for me.
And some personal projects
that reflect my values.
I would add to that,
when you mentioned
that your robot
is your web development.
When you are more
detached from things,
don't you think that you are a bit behind
when it comes to
all these technologies
moving quite fast?
When it comes to online intelligence,
when it comes to all the things
regarding the digital age
that you need for your robot?
So,
don't you think
that you are behind
in these topics?
Thank you for your question.
I am still choosing newsletters,
I am still following on social networks
that serve me,
I am still following people
who are in the space,
authorities and technologies
are developing very fast.
And I need to stay in touch
and therefore I have a certain space
when I devote my time to it.
But it is a very closed space
and I need
to develop
a large activity.
It is not so easy for me
to simply click on a web address.
I need to realize
that now is the time.
It is not automatic
and there is really a border
between technology and my time.
I know when this time is
and I am still in touch
but I don't get the warnings
that they will stop me at a given moment.
The fact that the React 19 version came out
on Monday morning.
So basically you have it
incorporated into your habits
that you deal with.
Yes.
Any questions
directly from the audience?
Because there are questions
in the chat.
Maybe we have some active viewers
on YouTube, but I don't think so.
Or?
In the back, admit it.
So you are sitting here.
What do you miss
from the digital world
when you are talking about
some of the digital tools?
What do I miss?
Yes.
I read it like this.
What do you miss
from the digital world
when you are talking about
some of the tools?
Or more precisely?
I think I try to use
everything good.
Good for me is
something bad for others.
That's it.
I don't know
if it answers the question.
I understood it like this.
At the beginning
you gave up everything.
But then you wanted
all the good things
that should serve you
as a tool,
that should help you
survive in the digital world.
Unfortunately,
it's true.
But the navigation in this world,
you choose the tools
that are good
and that served you before.
Except Counter-Strike.
Do you miss games?
I don't miss games
because I replaced this time
with some time
that is more profitable for me.
It was a stage in my life
when games were in first place.
But the good things,
I find them all the time.
I can't answer
this question.
Sorry.
Ask it differently.
I have the microphone here.
I think
this question
because it sounded like
you just got rid of
all the bad things
and all the good things
stayed with you.
But it also had
some advantages.
There was no black and white,
that I threw away
all the bad things
and all the good things stayed with me.
Maybe you had to
choose something good
to get some time
or something like that.
Isn't it something
that was good for you
but you had to give up
because you miss it now?
Thank you for the question.
I think I don't have
anything to say about Facebook.
It was a radical step.
I removed it.
It wasn't deactivation.
My profile doesn't exist.
There are only close people there.
I like to learn
some things from them.
When I said extreme step,
I said no to all these people.
Maybe Facebook is really good.
But at that point
in my life
it wasn't good
to have something
that is not good for me.
I'm thinking
of guilty pleasures.
Somebody can help me
with Slovak?
How to translate it?
What are your
sinful uses?
The newest
when I open sora.ch
I see those generated videos
from artificial intelligence
and it is a joy
It's not artificially created, but it's so perfect, almost perfect, that I finally caught myself, I spent maybe 20 minutes there and I felt very bad about it.
Inspiration as well, but also very bad.
I got goosebumps.
I started to get nervous.
But it's great.
Sorry, it's a tool for generating videos using artificial intelligence.
The modern tool that was created two years ago with the boom of artificial intelligence.
There were also tools that generate pictures, videos, texts and so on.
Everything is related to it.
And unfortunately, those videos are starting to be very, very convincing.
Unfortunately, fortunately, that's the point of view.
And that's the point of view.
It's either a tool or some other tool that controls me.
Or it controls the reality that we encounter around us.
Recently, they started to generate real text for those videos.
Until now, artificial intelligence didn't do it.
The text was so messed up and now it's really possible to read it.
So you can spend more time there.
That's the problem.
What are the disadvantages of digital minimalism in your opinion?
Hey, there can be the risk of scrupulence.
I think that solving the puzzle, whether I'm paranoid or not.
And whether I'm not solving these aspects in life in too much detail.
I think that's such a danger, I would say.
Not that it's a disadvantage.
And that's everywhere.
In fact, the danger of those extreme sides.
To be in the most extreme, perhaps.
Find the middle.
Disadvantages.
I really see it that way.
I come out of my system on paper.
And through that paper I solve my digital space and life.
Therefore, digital minimalism is something I don't think about.
And it's natural.
I simply know, I realize which digital tools have what role in my life.
And I evaluate it from the real world.
Not within the digital realm.
So it makes sense what I said.
I just read the question.
I should have the question, but I'd rather ask if it fits.
We can have one more question.
I'm also writing a diary.
And sometimes I think that it would be more effective
for a person to be able to find something.
To have it at least in some word.
But for some reason, it's a habit.
And maybe it's more pleasant.
I'm still doing it by hand.
And now I see that maybe there's some...
So this aspect, that it can be used better.
If you're looking for something, it's definitely much harder on paper.
So would you say anything to that?
Thank you very much for the question.
I definitely solved it in my life.
I think it's the same.
It's definitely in some points.
That paper.
And really in that method,
Bullet Journal specifically,
which helped me make this important step in my life.
So there's an index or content, as we have in books.
We simply know the index pages.
It's probably some kind of basic orientation within a book.
And the viewing can sometimes be wrong there.
So far, I personally haven't had such a need.
But I can imagine that in the future,
we'll want to get some ideas.
I won't know where the idea is.
The idea is in what year, in what month, in what day.
I think that in my life,
viewing means that I have to digitize my information.
And at the moment, I don't see a method that would allow me
to take my information from paper
and make it, let's say, locally on a machine.
It wouldn't go anywhere to the Internet.
Because I don't want it to be on the Internet.
That's the problem.
So really, the index has a great importance
when it comes to privacy and control.
And I never want to give up on it.
I don't see...
Maybe there's potential for innovation here.
There are also, I think,
Remarkable and various companies
that develop tablets
where we can digitize writing.
But again, there's privacy there
and the fact that it goes into the cloud.
So no, at the moment,
I say no to viewing.
I don't need this function.
And I'd rather save an hour or two
by listing pages,
when it's really that important
and I'll have to find it somewhere.
When you write it,
do you feel like you can remember it more,
feel it,
and then you know that you've written it?
I don't know,
like your brain works that way,
that it's maybe natural,
or that you create some kind of connection
between your hands
and maybe some kind of awareness
that you wrote it and so on,
and then you know that it's written there?
Does it work that way somehow?
Yes, the memory is much more
forced by the habit of writing things.
And that's why I think
that writing never disappears,
because yes, we try to digitize,
to make it more effective,
but in the process of making it more effective,
we come to some kind of life function
and we don't even realize it.
Simply put,
the memory is definitely more stretched
and I have a feeling
that there's a bigger order in my life
when I know that.
When I can write it.
Yes, therefore,
you need to be more aware of it.
And really,
when a person needs to write something,
four or two times,
you ask yourself
if it's worth it,
the performance of writing,
because when I click on it,
really,
the connection in the head
is not that strong
and I think it flows faster,
so I definitely don't know
how to write today, I think.
Okay, can you imagine
the evolution of Star Trek,
the ship diary,
and that you dictate it
and then you can easily look it up,
because there are technologies for it today.
For what?
Instead of writing in a journal,
you can dictate things,
as if you know a diary
that is actually spoken,
instead of being written,
and today there are technologies
that can actually do this.
Can you imagine
this kind of development
in the future?
Actually,
I'm still talking to ChatGPT
and,
it will help me a lot
when, really,
a person wants to speed up
the activity of
marking thoughts
and, simply,
there is the answer on the other side.
I don't know
how it affects the memory,
how it works,
when a person
says something
and doesn't write it down anymore.
I would like to try
to do such an experiment,
what it would actually mean
for my routine.
Would you take it
in a positive direction?
I would maybe add
to the digitalization
of the written diary,
so,
if you are mainly
talking about safety
and the fact that
it wouldn't reach anywhere,
I think that now
there are some local
LLM models,
which you can install
directly into your computer
and which will lead you
to extract the text
from the picture
and then you can put it
into a local document
or something like that.
So, I think
that we are not so far
from the fact
that it will be possible
to digitize it
quite simply
and if you have it,
basically,
it is always available
and you can scan it
or scan it
at any time
so, I think
that we are not so far
from the fact
that it will be possible
to digitize it
quite simply
and to have it
only locally
on hard disk
or not to send it anywhere.
For example,
I personally
use writing
on a diary
which is called
Obsidian
which generates
Markdown files
which,
if I don't want to,
I don't have to send them
to the cloud.
So, I sort of
deal with it
in this way
but,
as you have already
mentioned,
even when
something is being said
or when
the diary is being made
with the spoken word,
that is another thing,
that even
when
there are
LLM models
which know
the speech
you can put it
into
some
kind of
digital form
which can be
searched for.
So, I think
there are
some possibilities
which will not be
such a problem
in the future
and it is
one thing
with the other
that it can be
combined like this.
Thank you
for the interview.
It sounded
very nice.
Maybe
my paranoia
is that
I would probably
need some
personal hardware
which is never
on the Internet.
I would probably
solve it like this
with a health code.
We don't see
what happens
with the information
in real life.
I don't want
to digitize it.
It is simply
my personal space
and that is where
the border
between me
and technology
is created
and I think
it will remain
like this.
There is
no such
device
which would
allow
me to
separate
the diary
and the speech
I don't know.
A hole in the market.
I don't know
how to
put it
in words.
But I think
we should
ask the audience
a question.
Apart
from the people
in the audience
have you met
people with
a negative reaction
to the way
you have
been
going?
Yes.
Yes,
many times.
It is very
polarizing.
Some people
really don't
understand
how I
grew up
in my life.
I think
the starting point
in life
influences
the way
of the individual.
And I have a feeling
that there are
many young people
who go
the same way
as me
and the more
sophisticated
algorithms
we see
which
always
know
to get
more attention
from us.
And really
when a person
grows up
today
he can grow
to a similar
level.
And that is
what I would
like to say.
Maybe.
Hello,
I am Tomáš.
I would like
to ask
if you
could
come back
to your
childhood,
would you
need
something
different
from your
parents?
And then
the question
is what
would you
advise
parents
towards
children
in digital
freedom?
Or other
members
of your
close
circle?
Thank you
for the
question.
Hey,
certainly
not.
My parents
did everything
they could.
I can
say that
one hundred percent.
My hard
head was
very there.
I was
strict
and I
told myself
what I would
do.
And so
it is
how I
spend
my time.
And today
they are
satisfied
because they see
that I have
chosen,
thank God,
the other
way.
I try to
bring
society
not
fun
by playing
games and
looking
at me
and paying
sponsors,
but I
try to
solve
some
logical
problems.
I am not a
psychologist
and I am
afraid to
talk a
little
about this
because
really
every
person is
different and
something
that is
different
from
another
person
works
on me
and it
is
hard
because
I have
personally
seen
other
people around
me who
can solve
these things
at this
low level
and it
was hard
to solve
it
by my
parents,
I really
realize that
and
I think
it is
a topic
rather for
a psychologist
I would say
and maybe
the cooperation
of psychology
with some
person who
went through
such a
story
like
it worked
that it
would take it
or rather not
because
they haven't
seen it yet
and haven't
experienced it
and you think
that 10 years
when it
would be
a common thing
when a parent
would be
an example
to his child
that it
could help him
pure speculation
very complex
question on
me at
this hour
and days
please
please simplify
Rado if
you know
more about
education
whether at school
or parents
children
but not
certainly
only from
one direction
I mean
more general
education
from
elementary school
specifically
this topic
maybe
they don't call it
digital freedom
but
somehow
otherwise
but something
similar
what do you think
about it
question
is that
it is important
to have
some space
where a person
can come
when he is at
the point
that he knows
that these technologies
do not serve him
but rather he serves
technology
that there is
some place
where he can
find these
resources
so education
certainly
whether it goes
through some
idols
in society
or it goes
through school
and through
school system
and state
or some other
institutions
in the way
it is
something
that
was created
even
when I
prepared
this meet up
that
digital freedom
is a
digital
problem
because
I started
to solve
this topic
in English
and I try
to have
as much
as possible
to have
it
that's
and that's the place I want to exist on the Internet, not on the Internet, but between people.
It's my story and I want as few people as possible to follow this path.
OK. Tomáš, would you like to rephrase the question? Because there was no answer.
I think it's more about the opportunities.
For example, I deleted my history on YouTube and there's nothing there.
So we can't look at anything that might bother you.
If the child doesn't have a tablet, he won't look at the tablet.
Or if there's no picture in the close-up.
I think it's more about the opportunities that we can adjust.
I'm not a parent, so I don't know.
It's more about the influence of the environment and the school.
Exclusion within the group is a bigger problem than not having a mobile or tablet.
But I represent it, so it's a discussion.
I don't have children either, but I have a similar story with games.
I think we should ask the child why they like to play games
and why it's like that.
Because every child can have a different reason.
For example, he wants to be the best he or she wants to be.
The winner of a tournament in Slovakia.
The master.
Or the child is simply interested in games or mechanics that attract the child.
And various other things.
But today the games are a bit different than they used to be.
When it was a single player.
There's also the socialization.
I play with other people.
We talk on the phone or with friends.
With classmates from school.
And someone said in the past.
It was also a child from school.
That we don't go out together.
Because everyone goes to play games.
All friends.
So we meet at home at the computer and talk on the phone together.
And other friends don't go out very much.
There is a closed system.
Maybe parents can somehow break it.
But if the children themselves don't want it.
I don't know what to do in that case.
Or whether it should be changed.
That's the problem with regulations.
I'm thinking.
What can a single person do.
When the group of people is simply four out of five.
They are behind the computer.
What can a single person do.
It would probably have to go up there.
That's something that's probably not visible in today's society.
There is Tik Tok.
And someone is trying to regulate it.
Because we see.
Those psychological consequences.
Maybe really hard rules.
As far as using devices at school.
Or at home.
I can't imagine it personally.
And it's a fight.
Yes.
I would go back completely to the beginning.
That you said.
When you went into that complete detox.
I don't know if I noticed.
How long did it take.
That you came back in some way.
To some social network.
Or to some application.
How long was it?
Half a year?
Month?
Week?
Or how long?
Thank you.
And another question.
How did the first days look like?
It must have been quite strange.
I imagine.
You sit.
You look.
What now?
Thank you for the question.
It wasn't like.
I look at the ceiling.
I don't know what to do.
Rather.
There is another part of the story.
It wasn't the only extreme decision.
That I made in that period of my life.
There.
I went.
Yes.
All in.
To some of my projects.
It didn't work.
And I wasn't productive.
And that was another reason.
Why?
Why did I decide to go this way?
Because.
I needed to know how to focus.
On what I need to do.
The first application.
It was.
As I mentioned.
When I don't have a diary with me.
I need to remember.
Those thoughts.
And so on.
During the run.
So.
I need it.
Some management.
And so on.
Or.
I had.
Any hold.
Everything.
In the letter.
And the memory.
Aand.
Of a day.
Healing days.
And it.
Was.
The first application.
Which.
Holding.
Temporarily.
This was.
A temporary estajun for.
My puzzle.
And what I later.
Transfer to.
The newspaper.
So it was.
The first application.
And it.
Danke 해요.
Muito rápido.
действительно Thus.
I saw.
Maybe they like it, but it didn't work for me, so I decided to go digital.
So it was a short period, but as far as a social network is concerned,
which is designed to attract people, when I decided to insert such an application into my life again,
it was probably, hey, maybe so, I don't know, three or four months, plus or minus,
I realized that why not use food, because others motivate me to move, so I'm going to use food.
That's how it can be.
I have a simple question, that if you, all of us here, or those who are watching this on YouTube,
would recommend one thing,
what would you have from what you implemented into your life,
what do you think gave you the most positive effects,
or what helped you the most in your digital transformation?
If each of us had to pick one thing, whether it's a diary, a screen time limit,
or what exactly would you recommend?
Thank you for the question.
On my way, that's probably me,
it's clear that it was to make radical decisions.
Simply, yes, one thing is to give up all digital tools,
but then, for example, to shut down Facebook,
not to think that the world will simply collapse when these connections stop working in the virtual sphere.
Really take the phone numbers of people I care about and contact them via the phone,
eliminate these types that are useless,
that don't serve people primarily.
So, to be radical is not just to deactivate for some time.
To really make these cruel decisions, I would say,
because, at least for me, it was not very easy to realize that Facebook is not worth living on,
and I don't know how many friends I have there, or who.
I think that people solve this a lot.
And you have to do the short thing.
The energy that I simply have at the end of using the application,
if it is not positive, why should it be in my life?
So, don't be afraid to step out and mention the problem that the energy is negative.
So, I really can't be present.
That's the first step I recommend to everyone.
Realize if I really live this moment.
For example, I'm here with you.
I can be here and my thoughts are present here.
Or rather, I'm drawn to some other world where there is isolation from me.
Radical decisions.
The last two questions.
How many hours of your day do you spend at the painting in a digital space?
Can you maybe distinguish that work is one thing,
and somehow strictly distinguish it?
Maybe you think that I measure these things, but...
You don't measure?
I don't measure it.
And...
Yes, I measure the time for projects at work.
And I have a very good view there,
that definitely at work eight hours a day.
At the moment, this project is really demanding.
And it demands.
But...
As for some free time,
I can say a lot.
I think one series, one part is enough.
Simply, that time is definitely not...
Ten hours.
I think it's definitely not a day.
If we count work as eight hours,
it's not just eight hours,
so six plus two hours of fun.
Good.
Eight hours of free time.
But take it like this,
that I simply work on a computer,
and that's the activity I do every day in the working week.
So...
This is how it looks today in the digital world.
And a completely practical question at the end.
Do you consider that you would have finished programming
and go to work outside of digital?
Apart from digital?
No, no, no.
I don't want to do such an extreme thing again.
Digital...
Digital definitely belongs to our lives.
No, no.
Like, yes, you have to make extreme decisions,
but again, in the field of technology,
you don't have to rely completely on technology.
I don't even want to say that this way of mine.
You really have to restart that relationship
when a person needs it.
And I restarted it,
and I simply see that technology,
has a great potential.
And I really want to show that you can get them under control.
And that's what I was trying to tell you today.
Thank you.
Thank you very much, Samo.
I have a feeling that your presentation
was just to spread the discussion.
I'm glad it turned out that way.
That's how I imagined it.
It looks like it would be,
that it would also be enjoyed in part two.
So sometime at the end of the year,
we can agree and talk about some improvements,
about optimization,
and maybe about how your project is going,
and whether you are already at the finish line.
So we're finishing the official part.
You can stay here, of course.
Of course, if you have any questions,
please do.
I look forward to seeing you on the month of April 24.
LinkedIn.
Don't forget to come.
LinkedIn Guru is coming.
Thank you.
We have Tatra's stickers too, right?
I forgot to mention that.
As always.